[Music]
hey everyone
thanks for tuning in and today it is
march 30th
2022. we're here in the actin flab
quarterly roundtable number one for
2022.
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at some of the links
here on this slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome here and we'll be following
video etiquette for live streams
today in the actin flap quarterly round
table number one for 22 we're going to
have a
first section after our intros on lab
scale updates
and then we'll talk about project scale
updates which are nested within the lab
scale and just close with some
preferences and expectations and through
and through we hope that you'll see many
affordances for participation
many extensive cues signals in your
epistemic niche that elicit action
that make you curious about something
that um
connect with your pre-existing
preferences or update them so that you
get involved with active inference or
possibly even the lab so whenever you do
see this or listen to it or some other
combination
feel free to go to activeinference.org
or
email us at activeinference gmail.com
and we'll be in touch from there
so we can begin with just some
introductions and warm-ups and it feels
so different to do this without a
paper that we've read before so for
these intros we can just say hi and
anyone can reflect on just like
how is your generative model updated
this quarter what did you perceive or
learn how did you change
and what might be something that you're
looking forward to as we carry on the
latter of 75 percent of 2022.
so
i'm daniel
and a researcher in california i think
my generative model updated and
fragmented into a thousand little pieces
with
coda and the way that we used formal
documents this quarter as opposed to
previous quarters but
it's cohering in a way that is actually
helpful i hope
so
i'll pass to alex
yes everyone i'm alex watkin i'm
one of the founders of the lab and also
researcher
at systems management school and from
latest time i feel
like we're sharing our generative model
more and more and hopefully
it will bring us to me to two new
developments
and they paste it to blue
hi everyone i'm blue i am an independent
research consultant in new mexico
um i think this quarter was pretty
special like the coda restructuring was
pretty awesome and
just contributing to building like lab
infrastructure in coda and in like
youtube with like videos and time stamps
and podcasts and i don't know it was it
was fun um i think probably the biggest
update was was the quantum paper because
that was pretty pretty epic um the one
that we just have discussed over the
last couple of weeks
um and in the next quarter i'm looking
forward to
having some more
quiet time less talking more viewing
that's what i'm looking forward to in q2
of 2022. and i will pass it to
yvonne
thanks blue
yeah because he's very nice i i'm i'm a
violinist in uh
many now
and we finally run
system thinking study group
this uh
this water
and i hope
lab participants enjoyed and i see it
that they do
and i hope we
run next quarter
another
study group and it will be on like
conference
so that it
is
hi yeah a lot going on um
i'm becoming a little less guilty about
skipping at least half of the activities
but i get to hear at least at least to
read the papers and listen to the live
streams and there's lots of work going
on with the transcript which is very
gratifying even if daniel no longer
believes himself about how valuable it
is to do the print transcripts and put
them in in service i still am sticking
with the 10 000 times more value from a
transcribed talk than
just a youtube audio with pictures
so who haven't we heard from
stephen
hello yeah we're still here we're still
standing sort of so that's great
i'm here in toronto
um for me i'm appreciative
for certain of the capacity the labs
offered
the connections the conversations the
ability to
bounce the ideas and that's been
really really helpful and um
particularly with like mark's uh sones
and a lot of these ideas with quantum
which
at first i thought some might be quite
abstract
we're starting to synthesize and find
ways to
to pull them together and so i'm hoping
that can be used now i'm working with
some embodied
workshops and taking that into
communities and letting this work inform
how i coach
how i facilitate
how i
try and explain
that's the hard bit but uh i wasn't that
and
it
could but shouldn't go without saying
just massive appreciation to everybody
who
does and continues to show up for
active lab
you see the tip of the iceberg on the
live streams but there are many others
so
as we continue to
formalize and determine and reduce our
uncertainty about what kind of thing we
are here we'll hopefully have clearer
and clearer ways to source attribution
and to
show recognition for all the people who
contribute in just the million ways that
are possible
from beginner to very familiar
so we will just provide a brief overview
of active lab from a narrative
perspective before we jump into our
strategy discussion so in 2020 towards
the middle and in the ends some of us
wrote a paper in uh september was when
it was published on active inference and
behavior engineering for teams which was
addressing a gap that we perceived in
the literature which was the
relationship between active inference
framework and remote teams and
communication
at the end of that year after thinking
about what our next steps would be after
that paper we
thought that something like an active
lab would be cool so we sent out an
initial call for collaboration
during all of 2021 was our first year of
active lab project operation
and the projects were in the three
organizational units of education
communication and tools
this year in 2022 which is what we're
going to be talking about
today
a lot has happened at both the lab scale
and the project scale so we're going to
first talk about the lab scale and the
two pieces under lab scale updates are
going to be the initial release of the
lab strategy document and we'll also
discuss the initial advisory board
cohort and then we'll go into the
project scale and discuss some of the
ongoing projects that
have resulted in all kinds of
deliverables and outputs
so first to the lab scale
alex would you like to talk a little bit
about just from a high level strategy
yeah thanks
[Music]
i think as everything in our lab we are
trying to do
things in some
new ways
[Music]
that was not using before and also
trying to
put it on some state-of-the-art terrace
and approaches
so as for strategy we consider strategy
no not as a
concrete
document but as a ongoing process
which will be
which will have a
quarterly reviews and updates
and uh
on high level we are following open
handedness approach
um
so
for for who is interested it's now can
be put
can be approached from
developments of canada stanley
and we're trying to avoid using classic
objective missions goals and
other corporate stuff so we are trying
to see
in the focus of the future we are trying
to see some stepping stones that we can
make
next steps
and also for sure
as from the beginning we use active
inference not only
as a research field but also trying to
implement
and use concepts from where such as
preferences and
expectations and also we consider that
all our activities
are on the different scales so we need
to follow and understand how it's
applied on different scales
so thank you
so we will now go through
the current state of the strategy
document and just anyone here feel free
to raise your hand and
of course anyone watching along feel
free to write questions and we'll get to
them
so
pause the video or check it out to read
the full text here but just to summarize
our strategic document preamble
in active lab we're directing our
attention to different phenomena across
multiple scales
and the scales that we're most
interested in or the ones that we are
heuristically using are the personal the
individual human scale
the lab scale that's active lab scale
and then the community or the niche or
the environment scale which is the
epistemic surroundings of the lab
and what's special about the lab scale
is that is where the lab can implement
policy
we can emit
actions that are perceived as sense
states by individual people or by the
external community and that may or may
not change their policy selection but
the lab scale is where strategy happens
because that's where we can actually
implement policy selection
and we're taking this
multi-scale
nested
systems perspective
to
five different aspects of actinflab and
those five aspects that we're going to
talk about in the next few slides are
education research
outreach and engagement
methods and open-endedness
any
general comments before we continue
okay so actinflab is an educational
nonprofit
this plays out at all scales as all
things do
but we're especially interested here in
the personal scale in educating
individuals
in having individuals that learn and
update their generative model
and also respecting just the tremendous
diversity of active inference journeys
that different individuals are coming in
and through
relationship with the active inference
lab
and at the more community scale
our educational efforts are oriented
towards reducing research debt
and increasing the applicability and the
comprehensibility and the rigor and
accessibility of active inference and
related ideas
any comments on education
okay
the second aspect
of the lab is the research aspect
and here it also plays out at the
personal and at the community scale
at the personal scale we hope to provide
a niche that scaffolds and catalyzes the
research projects by participants which
is something we'll come back to
later but
we both do research in the lab as well
as on the interface and just hope to
motivate and
create a space for people to share their
individual research updates
and at the community scale
we're recognizing that research is
carried out alongside ongoing
discussions about responsibility and
ownership and many many other
terms so
there we hope to
learn
practices and improve and give our own
twist on what the future of science open
science
decentralized science dsi just science
with no adjectives and education what
will research and education be in our
future stephen
thanks daniel yeah this is really
helpful
to to read and also
the fact that we've got lots of people
from different backgrounds
coming together we we're able
the research that's happening is is
quite trans-disciplinary
and um
or it's been informed by lots of
different ideas so there's a kind of a
mixture of
those processes so it's helpful to have
the systems engineering
work that we'll probably come to later
but that's helpful in
letting us get a feel for how the
research doesn't get siloed as purely a
paper but okay how could that be bounced
off
to maybe make a difference in the world
in ways that maybe people who don't even
know active influence
find that they're
using something differently because
active imprints has helped
the way that their practice is shaped so
i like that
awesome
the third aspect is outreach and
engagement
and the active inference lab is working
on a global scale with a participatory
model so at the personal scale we
welcome all participation and engagement
and that means all time zones and spoken
languages and
preferences and what people want to do
and where they're at with active
inference participation in a sense
begins with where the participant is
and there's of course more that i hope
everybody can say and add and show not
tell or show antel
if they've brought enough for the class
in the coming years and then at the
community scale we also seek to be part
of a emerging landscape of high quality
science communication and participation
and inclusion in research and projects
around topics like active inference
which is what we're most
attuned to in our regime of attention
but that doesn't mean we only talk to
active inference people
so we hope that our outreach and
engagement is
meaningful and sustained and impactful
any comments on outreach and engagement
okay
methods
the active inference lab applies
state-of-the-art methods across domains
that refers to
the methodology of active inference and
the emerging tools and ways that we have
of working with active inference as well
as other methodologies like for project
management for education for
communication etc
so at the personal scale
we're educating participants so that
they can grow their expertise in
different disciplines and also develop
as a person holistically like keeping it
balanced you're not going to stay up and
finish reading every single active paper
so
staying balanced and having
methodologies that help us be
performant but also balanced are quite
important
and then at the lab scale we hope to
implement the
cutting edge
the pareto optimal the bayes optimal
methodology which includes our switching
strategies
and
we fix typos
on the fly that's what editable
documents allow
our affordances
as an organization
are the methodologies that we
scaffold in projects
so especially at the lab scale
we hope that we use methodology that's
powerful and facilitates
collective intelligence and also
clarifies the distinction
or the delineation the partition perhaps
even between those who are following
along and listening to live streams
reading the papers in the game that's
awesome and then those who actually
onboard into the lab and eventually
have a role
in a project
will be able to increasingly
be clear about what that means through
the uses of different
systems
ideas like practices cases
responsibilities and concerns yes yvonne
yeah so thank you i would like to add
that if we compile
uh methods and outreach
so the lab
provides a lot of opportunities for
the understanding of active fingerprints
and we provide a lot of tools and
for those who already
[Music]
participate in
in the lab and but those who just
start to deep inside the active
influence
awesome
and
the
last but not really the last aspect is
open-endedness
as alex
mentioned earlier and has been
bringing and reminding us all of since
the beginning
that active lab is on the path of
open-endedness
it doesn't mean that we sit and wait
where the road forks or when we have
uncertainty about the future those are
fundamentals and in fact open-endedness
is action amidst uncertainty
so at the personal scale we recognize
and support the open-endedness of the
personal journey of individuals who are
learning and applying active inference
so even if you don't know exactly where
you're headed or what your finish line
or your milestones your checkpoint looks
like if you don't even know what your
preferences are or you're unsure about
some other parameter in your generative
model that's all good
at the lab scale
our strategy
is to say it is a work in progress
would be
to almost assume that there would be a
final strategy
but rather our strategy is an ongoing
process
that will always be updating
in response to changes in the niche and
the effect that our actions have over
multiple time skills
so
we do recognize and utilize approaches
to achieve short-term
success and realizing products and
deliverables over short terms but also
there's a time and a space and a place
for thinking about active inference and
the active inference lab
in deeper time and that is especially
where diverse participation and our lab
advisory board
come into play which we'll talk about in
a second and then just lastly at the
community scale
it's true in principle that active lab
can participate in
various kinds of activities that might
be beyond education research and
outreach and engagement
we will always be considering those
opportunities in a case-by-case way
and assessing whether it's something
that fits best within the markov blanket
and the kind of thing that active lab is
or maybe some thing else could exist
that could play that role in the
ecosystem
yes dave
okay stephen
i'm interested by that way that the
ecosystem this this question of what's
in the markov blanket
and the non-equilibrium steady state and
what's in the niche and we um
those three things are kind of dynamic
so
i think over time
looking at the way the world is and
without getting too evangelical there's
lots of
big you know there's big uh claims made
about active inference and its potential
and
as we've been having conversations we've
seen a lot of things at scale come up
which is quite exciting conversations
around
that but often maybe a little bit fuzzy
a little bit
conceptual so i think
some of the stuff that's going to come
out there the lab's going to be
spinning off as much as it might be
holding on to
excellent thank you
so that concludes the discussion on the
strategy update the second lab scale
update
is to
mention our advisory board so
this information can be found at
our website activeinference.org and on
the top right head over to where it says
advisory board
the advisory board is a
insight and guidance board it's not a
managerial board
and it exists to help the lab make
better strategic decisions
so we engage our advisory board
participants in terms of their expertise
different recommendations and questions
they have for the lab and we
recognize and hope to draw on and
synergize with their experience in many
many different areas
we have an image here from
kirchoff at all 2018
about nested
systems
and about the way that as systems
develop for example as potentially a um
over developmental time a zygote goes
from being a single cell enclosed by a
lipid bilayer towards increasingly
um
ramified levels of embryonic complexity
or similar transitions could be
happening over evolutionary time
something like that is occurring as we
elaborate and build the active lab
we have an awesome
initial cohort of the advisory board
and it includes bradley alicia john boyk
matt brown
john clippinger scott david jeff emmett
chris fields
carl fristen
raphael kaufman anatoly levanchuk
rosalyn moren alba serrano
cheryl van hoof tim verbellen swann webb
and michael zargham and we have already
received really important and meaningful
feedback from them and really appreciate
it and for those who are interested in
the kinds of work that we're up to and
might have experience
in a certain domain that could be
helpful for example related to
educational non-profits then
perhaps get in touch with us but this is
a major change to the lab scale to
introduce an advisory board
and we're off to a fun start with them
so far so we look forward to just seeing
how that continues
any other comments on active at the lab
scale
or we can head to the projects
okay so
as we head through these projects
feel free to raise your hand to any
point if you want to add a comment or a
question and as a participatory lab
those who are listening and you've made
it this far recognize that all of these
reflect the contributions of
participants and reflect affordances for
you to contribute further even if only
to reduce your uncertainty about the
documentation or the way that something
is occurring so hopefully if you're
listening to this string of symbols
know that you can participate and
perhaps you even should
we're going to talk about a few
different projects today in fact 11
difference of them
and you can see loosely on the left that
these are
in three organizational units
edu comms and tools
but the project scale is really where
the team and the roles and the practices
occur so we're highlighting the project
scale and the project is also the unit
of granularity where you can really get
involved and make a contribution so
showing up for our synchronous
organizational unit meetings
is an awesome way to kind of paint a
first coat and to be exposed to many of
the projects but by and large the
contributions happen at the project
scale and asynchronously so
all backgrounds all time zones all
levels of commitment
everyone is welcome to get involved with
these projects which we're going to go
through now they're going to be the
active inference ontology the active
inference course
internal educational initiatives like
the systems thinking reading discussion
group and ontology working group active
inference journal
research updates
live streams
podcasts social media
active block reference robotics and
embodied and active lab meta modeling
on we go to the ontology
we've just recently
pushed an update to the active inference
ontology
and it's available at this coda link
here
the goal of the active inference
ontology is to increase the
accessibility and impact of active
inference by increasing clarity and
interoperability and expressivity and
all these other good things about terms
and ideas
and when you go to this site you'll find
that there's a explanatory preamble
and what this ontology release contains
primarily are two different kinds of
things proposed definitions and
translations so first the proposed
definitions
this is what the proposed definitions
look like for the core terms
the terms are on the left column here
and then everywhere there's an at and a
blue is like a clickable link to another
term so it's kind of like how
dictionaries use other words in that
language and it will say a is kind of
like b except it's different than c and
so that's what the definitions are
they're natural language
answers to the question what is
x
and so these proposed definitions are
currently in natural language but there
are other ways to develop them more
formally the proposed definitions are
there for those who just say well what
does this term mean
it also helps with computationally aided
sense making and then the second piece
that is in this current release of the
ontology
is the translations
and so here's the current view of the
top of the translations table
so we have the term in the english on
the left side
and then we have
so far complete translations of the core
ontology terms into spanish portuguese
french italian
czech russian and hebrew and some german
and some others that are sort of
beginning
so especially if you have fluency or
friends with fluency in some of these
languages but especially
new and different languages this is a
really awesome opportunity to translate
some terms which are mostly normal
natural language terms
into another
human natural language
and that will facilitate the ability to
for example deploy
educational information
or transcripts in their translations
do it in a way that's rigorous and
accessible and meets people where they
are in terms of their language fluency
yes dave
okay
so
that's the active ontology um project
where we're
developing a participatory
um ontology for active inference terms
stephen
could i just ask
not putting you on the spot but if i was
to ask you like what what areas have
been the most challenging or the most um
kind of uh
like uh
most most difficult to overcome and um
what what are the sort of questions that
are still
being grappled with on the ontology you
know and which ones have we overcome
already and which ones are still
sitting there in the background i'm just
curious if you've got any thoughts on
that
yeah good question i'll give it a
thought and then anyone else is welcome
to if they want
one
interesting thing is these definitions
although many papers do sometimes define
their terms
either in the text or in a box or in a
glossary that doesn't mean that the way
that the terms are defined are coherent
or compatible or consistent
and a lot of times it's like a yes and
someone defines it one way and someone
else just kind of takes a different spin
on it but other times we have come
across several situations all together
all of us at least here where there were
incompatible seeming
uses of terms and perhaps that happens
with all kinds of linguistic elements so
that was one interesting thing was that
it's not just like we're looking through
papers and copying sentences there's
actually a really
powerful process of the discussion that
we had focusing week by week on just a
few terms or one term where we were
seeing all the different ways that
different terms are being used inside
and outside of active inference and just
trying to work towards some kind of
grip on that blue
so
one of the biggest challenges that i
think we face um is dirty and incomplete
data
which is like pervasive across fields
and disciplines everywhere so i mean
trying to be
the bridge to fill the gaps to make the
data to complete the data like and
i mean there's always opportunities that
people want to get involved
like in filling out the data like
helping us to complete um you know to
have a complete uh picture of which to
metamodel
awesome and there are other
columns and features of the ontology
that we're working on in the lab for
anybody who wants to get involved like
correct examples just simple declarative
concise positive examples of terms being
used correctly
that's awesome
incorrect examples
people who are using
sentences it doesn't have to be caught
in the wild but it could be but just
generating sentences that are like
counter examples
um
can be very helpful for both humans and
computers in their learning and so we
have
examples um counter examples formalisms
connecting core terms and other terms to
equations and papers and connecting it
with the literature corpus so there's so
many angles those with
curiosity and expertise in active
inference and or ontology should
absolutely get involved with this which
will be a long-term project of the lab
and we hope to find new ways of
deploying it and just to give one
little contextualizing slide here
um
this entire continuum
can be considered to be different
types or grades or like a taxonomy of
ontologies
and so ontologies in their most informal
can be as simple as a list of terms or
glossaries the sources or what we have
right now with the current release which
is like a principled informal hierarchy
and some relationships amongst terms and
that's what we have right now with the
proposed definitions and translations
we're also working with the ontology
working group which we'll talk about in
a few minutes on formalizing that
ontology for example using sumo and suo
kif
and thinking about how do we integrate
the ontology with course development
with knowledge engineering and
literature integration so
some of the many things that people can
look forward to
okay
on to the second project which is the
active course
so
in the active course project
we are seeking to create a learning
platform that embodies the principles of
active inference and facilitates the
learning of its principles and concepts
to learners of many different
backgrounds
and this is something that we are not uh
too
far down the road on but are eagerly
looking forward to
especially in light of some recent
epistemic changes in our niche which
we'll talk about soon but there's a
massive potential for active inference
education and we hope to have course
offerings and educational experiences
that meet that opportunity alex
yeah just a quick note to avoid possible
misunderstanding that
notion platform here is not like for
some it platform
but more about a set of educational
services
which will be supported to improve
learning
affordances
yes
good call thanks for clarifying that
so
if you're interested or curious about
course design education
education in a participatory way
non-profits those are all excellent cues
for people who would like to come on
board and help in a serious way for this
course as we start to think about what
it can be
okay
third project
we have several internal educational
initiatives in active lab
and so
on the left
we see the systems thinking reading
discussion group and on the right
ontology working group the owg
alex or anyone would you like to
describe or give a note on either of
these sides
i just want to say that from very
beginning we consider that we should
not only
learn and
educate active inference but also
to learn
as you mentioned before state-of-the-art
practices
and system thinking was one of the
main discipline from the beginning what
we think is very useful for
collective work especially in remote
mode
so it's great but now
more and more people
start learning and it
definitely will improve our
communication and speed up our
activities on the projects
thank you yes
yvonne has been facilitating the systems
thinking reading discussion group strdg
and we have an intrepid group of
participants who are
working their way through this online
course and having regular discussions
and asynchronous conversations as well
around it
and as alex said this is really
important for the ways that we work
together and communicate
and on the right side we have the
ontology working group so
previously we were discussing the active
ontology as a project where we're
talking about active inference terms and
how they're related
in the ontology working group
we are increasing our competency in
computational ontology
and what that has looked like primarily
has been working with the sumo suggested
upper merged ontology system
in suo kif
and working through the
textbook of adam peace
and this has been an awesome experience
dave has
made a massive amount of contributions
and ontological um
limericks
of different formats
and that has also been a great
learning experience that hopefully will
fold back in towards
improving the active inference ontology
but it's also just a learning initiative
and that brings us to
a
ongoing learning initiative which is the
release
literally
in the last several days of
the textbook by thomas parr giovanni
pizzulo and carl firsten
it's the active inference
textbook
and we asked well what can the active
lab do for slash with
around
the textbook
do you want to join a textbook group
not just a reading group just a textbook
group
because we are going to be organizing
cohorts of textbook groups
and you can email us for the form if you
don't already have access to it but you
will fill out a form
that asks whether you'd like to join
an upcoming textbook
group cohort and it will be done in
groups in cohorts
yes you're ready or no you'd like to
perhaps hear about that affordance in a
few months
we ask for name email address and
country whether you have a textbook or
not and then just for you to provide
several sentences or more on your level
of familiarity and your interest in
active inference
and all backgrounds and familiarities as
with all activities are welcome this is
going to be a really
awesome
experience i think to work through this
textbook and
see it as just
one pebble on the ant hill or the tip of
the iceberg or any other metaphor that
people use for the way in which this
textbook will both be
a visible
and centralizing artifact as well as
something that is really only a few
hundred pages long and it's a relatively
small physical book
so
it's just the beginning it's not the end
of active inference and
those in the textbook groups will
realize that and enact it
any comments on internal educational
initiatives
alright
number four
the active inference journal
so in this project we are publishing
knowledge artifacts so that they are
searchable indexable and citable
most recently in the active inference
journal we uploaded a second improved
version
of the transcript
of the carl fristen symposium applied
active inference symposium
that was in june 2021
and from that we are improving our
methodology
that we learned and learned by doing in
that first symposium transcript process
and applying that to other event
recordings for example guest stream 16
with mark solms and live stream number
40 with a quantum
free energy principle so um
the journal is going to be a great place
where we continue to
build a participatory pipeline for
improving
and written dissemination
anything that anyone wants to add on
this
yes dave
yeah i sent the uh
the original paper and the
three
uh video segments to sean carroll along
with a summary of the three
big points in the summary
he says this is cool i will check it out
uh which i'm sure incentivizes the
gentleman who volunteered to go through
our transcript and make it more
presentable to get through that and um
then we can send that to the very busy
doctor carol who just has a new
appointment he is something like
the
the chair of the philosophy of science
at johns hopkins
so
all his pain of being denied tenure is
paying off apparently
and he may pay off he already i think
gets along very well with professor
tristan
he uh he says i have never had to work
so hard in an interview with somebody
who is so knowledgeable and well spoken
and anxious to communicate
awesome
yeah
and it's a great example of a project
that
increases accessibility for example by
taking um two or six hours of youtube
discussions
and making them searchable
and translatable and then also reduces
research research debt because we can
have somebody spend three or seven hours
improving and curating a manuscript and
finding oh when somebody mentioned this
paper here's that specific citation
that multiplied by thousands of people
searching for that paper maybe they have
access maybe they don't maybe they
misheard the name
there's so much that we can be proactive
about in terms of making our knowledge
corpus really accessible and meaningful
and woven according to
modern practices
okay
awesome work though dave and others on
the journal maria and others as well
okay
on um
five we have research updates
so this is not a project that we
actively steward per se in the lab but
this is just capturing research that's
in progress and finished by lab
participants
so just to highlight
a few
papers and products that have been
released by active inference lab
participants but not necessarily as an
active lab project in the last few
months so by
avail gwen and carlu aka serval aka
icarus uh the paper cognitive agency in
sociocultural evolution
and then a
awesome collaborative paper that we
wrote
with myself shawn arhan rj shadi
avel blue yvonne sid
ahmed yaakov caleb and alex
where we
talked about decentralized science desai
we integrated some of the more
technological perspectives on dsi for
example related to web 3 and blockchain
and juxtaposed that with some of the
bottom up the view from the bottom
participatory sense-making
and epistemic commons and
produced an active entity ontology for
science eos that we hope will allow us
to
have a way to model some of these
complex epistemic ecosystems in the
coming
months so that's just some of the
research and there's other
awesome research that's in progress
okay
on to yes stephen go for it
yeah be curious i think this uh work
with situated sense making
for decentralized science is really
really interesting um and i think
there'd be ways that the other
areas of sense making which this can be
uh helpful to bridge that active
influence
generative modeling approach with uh
other ways so i'm
i'm really glad that you did this work
actually as a group and uh i think it's
gonna help
tell another story which might have been
a bit too hard to tell from the ground
up but now you've got a bridge so thanks
okay on to six
so
we had
awesome
live streams as usual in this quarter
at the
coda dot io
active inference lab active lab you can
find the past and upcoming live streams
we had
uh several guest streams and other kinds
of streams but most of our streams in
the last few months were the paper
discussions so in live stream number
35.01 and two so as with all of these
there was a zero a background and
contextualizing video
that was prepared in the weeks leading
up to the dot 1.2 discussions which are
participatory group discussions so if
you ever see a paper where you want to
be in the dot 1 or the dot 2 and be part
of a group and you don't need to say a
ton no one's gonna call on you you can
ask anything you want provide any
perspectives you're always welcome to
join that way and then something that's
incredibly helpful for the lab is to
commit
assuredly ahead of time
and contribute to the dot zero making
the slides and helping contextualize the
paper
ahead of the dot one and the dot two so
we in the last few months have talked
about
in number 35 we talked about a tale of
two architectures free energy its models
and modularity
check out the live streams to learn more
i won't even attempt to summarize the
papers other than just to state their
titles
in 36 we discussed modeling ourselves
what the free energy principle reveals
about our implicit notions of
representation
we then dove a bit into the technical in
37 with free energy a user's guide
in 38 discussed the evolution of brain
architectures for predictive coding and
active inference
in 39 discussed morphogenesis as
bayesian inference
a variational approach to pattern
formation and control in complex
biological systems and then in 4d we
discussed a free energy principle for
generic quantum systems which was
as anybody who was there
before or during or after it happened
can a test was quite a special and
interesting experience
and just to show what that coda page
looks like if you head over there you'll
see the upcoming streams here we are in
the end of march it's not in the live
stream section it's in the um
round table
section
here we are right now
but in live streams you'll see the
papers that we're going to be discussing
in the coming months
so if you're interested in any of these
upcoming papers please get involved in
the dot zero or the dot one and two
if you're interested in inviting anybody
or yourself being a guest on a guest
stream
that's always an affordance these are
like one off
or
small series
that can be on active inference research
or related topics and we've had some
great
discussions in the last few weeks on
guest streams
we have model streams and math streams
that are for presenting some of the
formal and model based components of
active inference and org streams where
we talk about organizational principles
and organizational design so
those are just some of the live streams
that we've had and it's been fun
so
especially if you want to give a guest
stream or if you can connect to somebody
who does want to or
encourage or recommend somebody or you
want to be a facilitator for someone
else to present or any other combination
of affordances let's make it happen
because we can get a lot of awesome
modifications in our niche
i think what they used to call making
content back in the web two days
so that's all for live streams
podcast
blue do you want to
give an update
sure so we are moving through the
podcast really revisits a lot of the
early live streams so like if you're
playing catch up like if you caught a
live stream you're like i should go
through the back catalog like maybe now
you're on live stream 20 or something
like uh the podcast starts with the
early episodes and i think we're through
episode
nine live stream number nine now
um so yeah check it out it's fun um also
a great chance to get involved if you
have like av expertise would love to get
some pointers also like i know some
stuff um i've been clipping the podcast
for a little bit so if you'd like to
learn like the basic things that i know
and want to get involved in
making the podcast
reach out um i could always use help if
you want to listen to more podcasts come
help me
make them
dave
yeah if you have uh listed the
podcast after nine that you're planning
to do i'd like to get that because i
want to get started
with uh just doing basic text conversion
on this if that assumes that this these
are the priorities is that correct
these are the ones that you that we want
to get in front of people
i don't i don't know what the priority
is there dave but i i will say like
there's definitely value to having a
transcript um
uh i actually looked at podbean who's
our podcast platform the other day and
they will transcribe our podcast for us
actually at 20 cents a minute so if you
really want to know what the value of
transcription is
just just the value to just put it into
text now i don't know if that comes with
with periods or punctuation or i don't
know what that output looks like but
there's definitely value to having a
transcript there i'm not sure that these
are necessarily the priority but it's
just going through the back catalog it's
helping me catch up
so i just kind of started where i wanted
to start
at the beginning why not start at the
beginning right i don't know
what what i love about these podcasts is
they're short
they're like from four
to maybe 15
or 10 minutes long
and
the first time that a speaker speaks
they introduce themselves
and there have been some probable
clippings and rearrangements which are
very subtle that help that listenable
piece
be like coherent like it's like an
extended thought even one that's
distributed across multiple speakers so
like
you hit play
listen to it
and then
you can think and reflect because
sometimes when it's two hours on a paper
it feels like it's like a rail car
coming through it's like every single
idea and thing and people say that they
pause the live streams and there's so
much and then also as the priorities um
that's something we can figure out and
discuss
but won't it be amazing when
the live stream is
you know the front car of that train
piercing into the future
doing it live
and then
there's transcripts for all the live
streams and that can be on one hand
connected to the ontology a transcript
of the live stream itself could exist
there could be some clipping and some
transcripts for the podcast so as we
develop our informational
ecology all of these kinds of
connections and tasks are in play it's
just a question of how late can you stay
up which
i've wondered about for a long time
dave needs no sleep um you know the
other cool thing about the podcast is
that it's slide free so where when
you're on the youtube watching the live
stream often it's associated with some
visual image and sometimes there will be
like a description of the image in the
podcast but it's nothing that you need
to like pull over and look at which is
sometimes if you're trying to like watch
the youtube videos on the long drive
it's like ah that might not be safe but
the podcasts are definitely um you know
commute friendly uh because you don't
have to
see anything you can just listen so
that's another it just offloads the
visual input as well good for the
treadmill stuff like that
great point
okay
on to eight
so some updates on our um
i'll just call it social media
we have
our twitter
with um
1359 followers we have about i think we
crossed 300 members in the discord
um over 770 subscribers on youtube
and some
[Music]
several hundreds of people
reached in facebook
and
anyone who is interested in automating
social media that would be an excellent
affordance blue
yeah definitely i was just you took the
words right out of my mouth and facebook
uh is very new so we have like just 40
likes on our facebook page so if you're
listening to this and you use facebook
regularly for whatever i mean it will
ping you to remind you about podcasts
and sometimes live streams sometimes i
say because like i said we need an
automator so that's your expertise and
you want to always be reminded about the
live streams uh get in touch
yes just to be able to preload a buffer
um
here in the front
car of the train
it's sometimes hard to clean up the
pieces and so if you're
feeling like that's something that's
interesting to you then there's many
opportunities to
have engagements on different platforms
and just
feel free to just
engage in the comments and in the
threads however makes sense
great enough with social media
um okay on to
nine
so now we're heading more towards the
tools part of this
discussion
primarily the work of jakobs meckle
has been just
excellent on active block prints which
is a package that we're developing in
order to facilitate cognitive agent
modeling
and if you look up
active block fronts on github you'll
find the open source repository
what we've done with active block prints
is implement active inference entities
the kind that you will see
graphically described in papers or the
kind that have been implemented in
python via pi mdp
and we
built upon pi mdp
as well as a complex systems modeling
framework called cad cad
and
by integrating the
active kernel
of the entity action perception loop
with the complex systems modeling
framework
we hope to have
engineering-grade approaches towards
modeling
complex cognitive ecosystems so
if you are interested in python or julia
or other aspects that are computational
related to active inference and you like
complexity and complex adaptive systems
and
everything
else that you might see on this slide
active block for instance is an open
source project so go ahead and
fork it
make your contributions and come get in
touch with us if you'd like to be a
little bit more in the loop
and
really looking forward to seeing
how this project develops in the coming
years
in
dot tools also we've been having some
awesome discussions around robotics and
embodied cognitive entities
so we have been characterizing
kind of like a literature review on
different cognitive agent modeling
frameworks so active inference is often
proposed as a unified
cognitive entity model
and so we've been just
curating many other cognitive agent
modeling frameworks from the past and
present
and then assessing them in terms of
their language what cognitive features
they implement whether they deal with
embodiment what is their mathematical
underpinnings and so on
and meanwhile characterizing some of
those cognitive features and elements
like anticipation memory counter
factuals abductive reasoning different
kinds of cognitive features or motifs
and then trying to understand how do
these different cognitive model
frameworks
line up on the rubric of wanting to have
expressivity
across all of these different cognitive
features and to integrate them
and that's a little bit more on the
um symbolic cognitive
we've also
been thinking a little bit about the
embodied whether the embodied and
spatial and bodily or the
embodied and robotics
so here is um a
screenshot from
the
work of jf cloudshire who's been an
awesome participant in this past
quarter and some
active
robots
that are
uh carl and andy i think people can
probably guess what their last names are
and um
[Music]
there isn't too much more to add here
other than um check out this woefully
under acknowledged channel
and work and if you're interested in any
of these areas like related to cognitive
modeling
and robotics and embodied cognitive
systems those are the kinds of things
that will be awesome to scaffold in the
lab
okay
and to our
final of the 11 projects
actin flab meta modeling so
uh actin flab meta modeling aka alma so
there's an a and an l and there's an m
and there's an a and i think that was um
jessica's suggestion because alma has
nice connotations as well
this project is using meta modeling
tools like coda
to provide the capacity for lab scale
generative modeling updates and
reconfiguring so the ability for the lab
to reflect and to modify itself and its
niche
in order to design the kind of
participatory niche that facilitates
successful policy selection by lab
members like what does the lab need to
provide the individual as the action
state of the lab sense state of the
individual in terms of the communication
such that that participant is
chill but also making the right
decisions that are productive
and
we're using primarily coda that's why
the font is bigger here
but we're also implementing the active
entity ontology for science that we
discussed on the research slide and
active block for ins just two slides ago
as a more formal way to get at some of
these meta modeling
and this is a figure from our 2020 paper
that first early paper on systems
engineering and active inference and
remote teams
where we also looked at the
informational niche the shared
informational niche of the team this is
their shared folder their shared code
document their formal documents their
drive the chat threads
that's the shared epistemic niche where
actions to modify the niche by one
participant
can then be like stigma g
modifying the environment so that
themselves later or other participants
then or in the future
take different action selection
as mediated by the way that that sensory
state updates their generative model
and then we have narrative and so we've
been very interested for a long time in
rhetorical and narrative approaches to
cognition
and so now we're
just beginning to see how some of these
approaches can come into play in the
context of active inference and in the
lab
so that's like the meta
on actin flab and this is also an
awesome
project set of affordances if you like
coda if you liked douglas hofstetter's
girdle escherbach
if you like
act infer serve all of these would be
great diagnostic cues that perhaps you
would like active lab meta modeling
yes steven yeah thanks for sharing i was
wondering how this also might even be
able to tie in in the future to uh
micro phenomenological
kind of modeling i that that kind of
approach so we've got the meta the
narrative the story
and uh hopefully maybe some sort of
micro phenomenological
approaches as well but i think we've got
to walk but we'll get there so thanks
when you said micro phenomenological i
thought oh like the experiences of
children
yeah
say hello um
cool
um
so that is it for the project
updates
they're
all
ongoing
let's just kind of
go over some
next steps
at the lab scale
several areas that we're especially
looking for assistance or contributions
on would be on the legal side
um for example potentially connecting
with a firm that would be interested in
providing pro bono assistance
who has experience with
education nonprofits
intellectual property
tech etc
and also helping our lab navigate a
course towards financial sustainability
whether through grants or other
mechanisms but just finding a way that
we can reward and stabilize the
contributions of participants
and then at the project scale
any and all participants who want to be
in the strange loop in the strange
attractor
want to be on the path towards
contributing to active inference lab as
they also grow and develop as an active
inferencer and as a person so if any of
these projects or
some other opportunity that you see and
want to take
the initiative on
any of these reflect affordances for you
so hopefully if you're listening this
far in a minute and six hours in or
wherever it's clipped out in a podcast
then just recognize that these are all
reflecting the past contributions of
participants
like yourself and
this is just an opening it's only the
first quarter of 2022
we're just beginning and so there's so
much in the
field and in the lab to be done
that there will be something to do
that's meaningful and chill and aligned
with your preferences and expectations
and availability just
believe it
okay
so that takes us close to the end
um and a little modification of our
common ending slide
where do we go from here what are people
still curious about learning and
applying
and what are we going to do differently
maybe in the next quarter
yes blue
so i think i already put it out there at
the beginning um but i'm really like
interested in not talking about things
anymore spending less time talking about
things and more time actually doing
things so that that's what i'm going to
do differently in the next quarter and
that's me as like on a personal scale
has nothing to do really with the lab
but it's i just want to just work now
i just want to put my head in the books
and get to it
awesome yeah sometimes like
it helps to get caught up through
conversation and just being in the
synchronous meetings
but
one hour per week is
um
not how we build
a course or not how we go through a
textbook and so
that is a very important balance to keep
in mind
um
stephen or dave any other thoughts
yes
or no
there's a lot of good work going on i'd
say just keep doing it
and talk about you know talk about
what's working well what needs to be
improved what the bottlenecks are we've
mentioned some bottlenecks and
[Music]
know sometimes uh maybe some of the fun
projects
that could be pushed back in favor of
some of the more difficult things that
actually
will end up being leveraged heavily the
i think of the ontology immediately
it may not be fun to slog through this
stuff but it's going to really pay off
when you get some
transitive closure
aspects of it
of course awesome
for those who are studying or curious
about active inference but feel kind of
like on their own whether no one else in
their local niche or network or lab or
university or organization is working on
active inference that's like one of the
most powerful things is just knowing
like if you have an idea that you're not
even going to pursue
but just somebody should do this or it
would be cool if this existed having a
space where you can add that pebble
and maybe down the road or maybe sooner
than you expect somebody else
seeing that pebble
is stimulated to act and so that's what
can happen when we have shared ways of
working and that's just what we're
beginning to see stephen
yeah sort of bouncing off that as well i
think i keep thinking about stages of
readiness which i i am
i'm normally working with community
participants who are marginalized but i
kind of
i've had that myself with like feeling a
bit marginalized feeling am i
like ready and there was like
a little jump but it can be a chasm you
know
trying to get to that stage and i think
that can be for a lot of people you
don't quite know on different things
whether you're
near that threshold or not and you're
often a lot closer
to being ready and you maybe just need
someone to give you a kick up the bum
and say just go for it you know but
having said that that's when you
appreciate the quality of
getting get getting some things under
your belt on the way to the line so i
think
uh like blue said like it's time to act
and um for me personally yes like
um the stage of readiness i'm at is
very different to where i was a year ago
for sure
both in my knowledge when i look back to
where i was but also in my heart
and that's a that's not an insignificant
piece of the equation so thanks
awesome i'll just wait one more minute
if anyone who's watching live has any
questions that they would like to see
addressed
but totally agree it's um
it's a multi-year
journey i mean we're all on a lifelong
journey of some sort but hopefully even
our active inference journey is
multi-year
and so
being able to connect
our policy selection our behavioral
decisions in the next
micro cicade of the eyes the next place
your eye is going to look the next
action you're going to take in terms of
opening up a hyperlink or reaching for a
book or a pencil
but being able to connect those very
rapid
actions
with a bigger
picture
and with the longer
temporal time scale
and acting amidst uncertainty that's
what active inference is
about
one aspect of it and so
if anything that you've heard
resonates just
hopefully see this
round table presentation as like
an invitation
less than a
uh stand and deliver because
there's so much openness in the area and
in the lab and
it
maybe can feel like one is starting late
but that's just
human knowledge development it's a
treadmill that's been going
and through coming together in the lab
we can actually leverage each other's
contributions and catch up on fields
that have thousands of hours of reading
and
hopefully get somewhere cool together so
um
dave blue steven and yvonne and alex
from earlier
and all the other lab participants big
thanks for this
amazing
quarter and
it's been a fast one
and
on to the next one
okay
bye
thanks all have fun
you